<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="tutorial_about-tutorial">
    <title>Introducing our project</title>
    <subtitle>Allow me to introduce Cineasts.net</subtitle>
    <para>
        Once upon a time we wanted to build a social movie database. At first there was only the name: Cineasts,
        the cinema enthusiasts who have a burning passion for movies. So we went ahead and bought the domain
        cineasts.net, and the project was almost complete.
    </para>
    <para>
        We had some ideas about the domain model too. There would obviously be actors playing roles in movies.
        We also needed someone to rate the movies - enter the cineast. And cineasts being the social people they are,
        they wanted to make friends with other fellow cineasts. Imagine instantly finding someone to watch a movie
        with, or share movie preferences with. Even better, finding new friends and movies based on what you and
        your friends like.
    </para>
    <para>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="cineasts.png" scale="80" align="center"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <para>
        When we looked for possible sources of data, IMDB was our first stop. But they're a bit expensive
        for our taste, charging $15k USD for data access. Fortunately, we found
        <ulink url="http://themoviedb.org">TheMoviedb.org</ulink> which provides user-generated data for free.
        They also have liberal terms and conditions, and a nice API for retrieving the data.
    </para>
    <para>
        We had many more ideas, but we wanted to get something out there quickly. Here is how we envisioned
        the final website:
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="cineasts_main.png" scale="80" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

</chapter>
