<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="tutorial_repository">
    <title>Repositories</title>
    <subtitle>Serving a good cause</subtitle>
    <para>
        We wanted to add repositories with domain-specific operations. Interestingly there was support for
		a very advanced repository infrastructure. You just declare an entity specific repository interface
		and get all commonly used methods for free without implementing a line of boilerplate code.
	</para>
	<para>	
		So we started by creating a movie-related repository, simply by creating an empty interface. 
        <example>
            <title>Movie repository</title>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[package org.neo4j.cineasts.repository;
public interface MovieRepository extends GraphRepository<Movie> {}
]]></programlisting>
        </example>
        Then we enabled repository supprt in the Spring context configuration by simply adding:
        <example>
            <title>Repository context configuration</title>
            <programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<neo4j:repositories base-package="org.neo4j.cineasts.repository"/>
]]></programlisting>
        </example>
<!--		Besides the existing repository operations (like CRUD, and lots of querying) it was possible to declare
		custom methods that were either annotated with queries or were named like a query. Those methods could
		be more domain centric and expressive than the generic ones.
-->		
		For simple use-cases like finding by id's this is good enough. So we first let Spring autowire our 
		<code>MovieController</code> with the <code>MovieRepository</code>. So we could perform simple persistence operations.
    </para>
    <para>
		We felt that a domain oriented repository would more useful, especially as it only exposed the needed operations
		under domain-specific (vs. generic) names.
        We then created the domain-specific <code>CineastsRepository</code> class, annotating it with <code>@Repository</code> and
        <code>@Transactional</code>, and injected the basic movie repository.
    </para>
    <para>
        <example>
            <title>Domain-specific repository</title>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[@Repository @Transactional
public class CineastsRepostory {
  @Autowired MovieRepository movieRepository;

  public Movie getMovie(String id) {
      return movieRepository.findByPropertyValue("id", id);
  }
}]]></programlisting>
        </example>
    </para>
    <para>
	    We went on exploring the repository infrastructure. A very cool feature was something that we so far only heard
	    from Grails developers. Deriving queries from method names. The simplest use-case could help us get rid of that
	    custom implementation for the <code>getMovie()</code> method. Impressive.
	</para>
    <para>
        <example>
            <title>Derived movie-repository query method</title>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public interface MovieRepository extends GraphRepository<Movie> {
  Movie getMovieById(String id);
}]]></programlisting>
        </example>
    </para>
    <para>
	    In our wildest dreams we imagined the method names we would come up with and what kinds of queries those could
	    generate. But some, more complex queries would be cumbersome to read and write. So in those cases it is better
	    to just annotate the finder method. We did this much later, and just wanted to give you a peek in the future.
	    There is much more, you can do with repositories, it is worthwile to explore.
	    <!-- TODO mention geo-queries, query-result projections ?? -->
	</para>
    <para>
        <example>
            <title>Annotated movie-repository query method</title>
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public interface MovieRepository extends GraphRepository<Movie> {
 @Query("start user=node:User({0}) match user-[r:RATED]->movie return movie order by r.stars desc limit 10")
 Iterable<Movie> getTopRatedMovies(User uer);
}]]></programlisting>
        </example>
    </para>
    
</chapter>
