<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="tutorial:setup">
    <title>Scope: Spring</title>
    <para>
        Being a Spring Developer, I would, of course, choose components of the Spring Framework to do most of the work. I'd already come up with the ideas -
        that should be enough.
    </para><para>
        What database would fit both the complex network of cineasts, movies, actors, roles, ratings and friends? And also be able to support the
        recommendation algorithms that I thought of? I had no idea.
    </para><para>
    But, wait, there was the new Spring Data project that started in 2010 bringing
        the convenience of the Spring programming model to NoSQL databases. That should fit my experience and help me getting started. I looked
        at the list of projects supporting the different NoSQL databases. Only one mentioned the kind of social network I was thinking of -
        Spring Data Graph for Neo4j, a graph database. Neo4j's pitch of "value in relationships" and the accompanying docs looked like what I needed.
        I decided to give it a try.
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Preparations - Required Setup</title>
        <para>
            To setup the project I created a public github account and began setting up the infrastructure for a spring web project using maven as build
            system. So I added the dependencies for the springframework libraries, put the web.xml for the DispatcherServlet and the applicationContext.xml
            in the webapp directory.
        </para><para>


<programlisting language="xml" ><![CDATA[
            TODO setup code?
]]></programlisting>

    </para><para>
            With this setup I was ready for the first spike: creating a simple MovieController showing a static view. Check. Next was the setup for Spring Data Graph.
            I looked at the README at github and then checked it with the manual. Quite a lot of maven setup for aspectj but otherwise not so much to add.
            I added just a few lines to my spring configuration.
    </para><para>


<programlisting language="xml" ><![CDATA[
            TODO config code?
]]></programlisting>

    </para><para>
            I spun up jetty to see if there were any obvious issues with the config. Check.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
