<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="reference_neo4j-server">
    <title>Neo4j Server</title>
    <para>
        Neo4j is not only available in embedded mode, it can also be installed and run as a server that is accessed
        via a REST API. Spring Data Graph provides two-fold integration for infrastructure.
    </para>
    <section>
        <title>Server Extension</title>
        <para>
            What is the use-case for writing server extensions? The REST API is a pretty generic representation of the
            Neo4j core API. It is nice for getting started and simple scenarios. For more involved solutions that require
            high speed and high volume access to the embedded graph database, writing a server extension that is able to
            process external parameters and return just the relevant information to the calling client is preferrable.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Neo4j server has two built in extension mechanisms.
            It is possible to add extensions to existing endpoints
            like the graph database, nodes or relationships - add new URIs or methods to those. This is achieved by
            writing <ulink url="http://docs.neo4j.org/chunked/milestone/server-plugins.html">Server Plugins</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
            For complete freedom in your implementation an <ulink
                url="http://docs.neo4j.org/chunked/milestone/server-unmanaged-extensions.html">unmanaged extension</ulink>
            might be the right solution. Unmanaged
            extensions are <ulink url="http://jersey.java.net/">jersey</ulink> resource implementations.
            The resources constructors or methods can get the <code>GraphDatabaseService</code> injected to execute the 
            necessary operations and return appropriate Representations.   
        </para>
        <para>
            Both kinds of extensions have to be packaged as a jar and added to the Neo4j-Server's plugin directory.
            Server Plugins are picked up at server startup when they provide the necessary 
            <code>META-INF.services/org.neo4j.server.plugins.ServerPlugin</code> file for Javas service loader mechanism.
            Unmanaged extensions have to be registered with the neo4j-server configuration.
            <programlisting language="ini"><![CDATA[
org.neo4j.server.thirdparty_jaxrs_classes=com.example.mypackage=/my-context
        ]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <para>
            Integrating Spring Data Graph into this setup is not so trivial because the graph database is not created
            by the spring context but already provided by the Neo4j-server. But a correctly set up and loaded
            spring context ist the requirement for spring data graph to work. By using the lifecycle support of
            Neo4j server extendsions it is possible to register the provided graph database with the
            spring configuration and also to expose certain spring beans (e.g. graphRepositoryFactory, graphDatabaseContext) to be
            injected via jersey into subsequent resources.
        </para>
        <para>
            This can be achieved by subclassing SpringPluginInitializer and providing the context-locations and the
            beans that should be exposed. The <code>SpringPluginInitializer</code> merges the graph database service
            with the spring configuration and registers the named beans as jersey Injectables.
        <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public class HelloWorldInitializer extends SpringPluginInitializer {
    public HelloWorldInitializer() {
        super(new String[]{"spring/helloWorldServer-Context.xml"}, "worldRepository","graphRepositoryFactory");
    }
}
    ]]></programlisting>
            It is still necessary to list the initializer fully qualified class name in a
            file named META-INF/services/org.neo4j.server.plugins.PluginLifecycle. Then the Neo4j Server can pick up
            and run the initialization classes before the the extensions are loaded.
    </para>

    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Using Spring Data Graph as a REST-Client</title>
        <para>
            Spring Data Graph can use the Java Rest Bindings which come as a drop in replacement for the
            GraphDatabaseService API. Just by configuring the <code>graphDatabaseService</code> to be a
            <code>RestGraphDatabaseService</code> pointing to the correct URL, a Neo4j-REST server can be used.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                The Java REST Driver is still under development, so performance and functionality might not be en
                par with Spring Data Graph.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>
</chapter>
