<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="samples">
  <title>Samples</title>

  <section id="samples_introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      Spring Data Graph comes with a number of samples.
      The source code of the samples is found on
      <ulink url="http://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-graph-examples">GitHub</ulink>.
      The different sample projects are introduced below.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="samples_hello-worlds">
    <title>Hello Worlds sample</title>
    <para>The Hello Worlds sample application is a simple console application with unit tests, that
      creates some Worlds (entities / nodes) and Rocket Routes (relationships) in a Galaxy (graph)
      and then reads them back and prints them out.</para>
    <para>The unit tests demonstrate some other features of Spring Data Graph. The sample comes with a
      minimal configuration for Maven and Spring to get up and running quickly.</para>
    <para>Executing the application creates the following graph in the Graph Database:</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="helloworlds.png" contentwidth="15cm" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section id="samples_imdb">
    <title>IMDB sample</title>
    <para>A web application that imports datasets from the Internet Movie Database (IMDB) into
      the
      graph database. It allows listings of movies with their actors and actors with their roles in
      different movies. It also uses graph traversal operations to calculate the Kevin Bacon number
      (distance to an actor that has acted with Kevin Bacon). This sample application shows the
      basic usage of Spring Data Graph in a more complex setting with several annotated entities and
      relationships as well as usage of indices and graph traversal.</para>
    <para>See the readme file for instruction on how to compile and run the application.</para>
    <para>An excerpt of the data stored in the Graph Database after executing the application:
    </para>
    <para>
        <screenshot>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="imdb.png" contentwidth="15cm" scalefit="1"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="samples_myrestaurant-original">
    <title>MyRestaurant sample</title>
    <para>Simple, JPA based web application for managing users and restaurants, with the ability to add
      restaurants as favorites to a user.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="restaurant.png" contentwidth="15cm" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

  <section id="samples_myrestaurant-social">
    <title>MyRestaurant-Social sample</title>
    <para>An extended version of the MyRestaurant sample application that adds social networking
      functionality to it. It is possible to have friends and to add rated relationships to
      restaurants. The relationships and some of the properties of the entities are transparently
      stored in the graph database. There is also a graph traversal that provides a recommendation
      based on your friends' (and their friends') rating of restaurants. </para>
    <para>An excerpt of the data stored in the Graph Database after executing the application:
    </para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="restaurant-social.png" contentwidth="15cm" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="restaurant-social-graph.png" contentwidth="15cm" scalefit="1"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>

</chapter>
