<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="get-started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>

    <para>NOSQL databases has come into focus only recently, even if some of them have existed for a few years by now.
	That's why this document will not only guide you through the relevant parts of the Spring Data Graph
	API, but also explain some key concepts of graph databases.
	</para>
	<para>
		After reading this document, you should be able to integrate Spring Data Graph into your existing or future applications.
		If there are any issues that you don't understand or think are explained in a too complicated way, please report back any
		problems or suggestions. Your input will also benefit future readers of this documentation. For details on how to get help
		and provide feedback, see <xref linkend="get-started:help"/>.
	</para>

    <section id="get-started:first-steps">
		<title>First Steps</title>
		
		<para>As explained in <xref linkend="why-sd-graph"/>, Spring Data Graph (Spring Data Graph) provides integration
		between the Spring framework and graph databases. Familiarity with the Spring framework is assumed as stated in <xref linkend="introduction"/>, and only
		minimally cross-referenced here. Graph databases and Neo4j in particular are explained in a bit more detail.
		The main focus of this document is however on explaining the steps needed to get a Spring Data Graph-backed application up and running.
		</para>
		  
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:spring">
			<title>Knowing Spring</title>
			<para>Spring Data Graph makes heavy use of Spring Framework's <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/spring-core.html">core</ulink> functionality,
			such as the <ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/beans.html">IoC</ulink> container,
			<ulink url="http://static.springsource.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/validation.html#core-convert">converter</ulink> API and the 
			<ulink url="http://static.springframework.org/spring/docs/3.0.x/reference/aop.html">AOP</ulink> infrastructure. While it is less important
			to know the Spring APIs, understanding the concepts behind them is essential.
			The Spring Framework documentation
			<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/documentation">home page</ulink> is a good starting point for
			developers who want to become more familiar with Spring Framework.</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:nosql">
			<title>Knowing NOSQL and graph databases</title>
			<para>The recent interest in NOSQL databases is mainly driven by the need to find the best suited storage solution for data
				structured in a specific way. It should fit the data, not the other way round. Another issue is the scalability of the
				database, especially with today's fast growing user bases. There are many NOSQL databases,
				and one should become familiar with the different concepts, advantages, and disadvantages before choosing
				a solution. A problem with the NOSQL databases is the different data access APIs that are provided. Spring Data aims at easing this burden by
				providing consistent abstractions over those APIs, leveraging SpringSource's experience and good reputation in this area.
			</para>
			<para>
				Graph databases are a particularly good fit for large networks of connected information (objects). They map objects to nodes and connections to
				relationships. Examples of such datasets are social networks, geospatial information, network layouts, and hardware or dependency graphs.
				Neo4j is the first graph database that is tightly integrated with the Spring Data Graph project.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:first-steps:samples">
			<title>Trying Out The Samples</title>
			<para>Spring Data Graph comes with a number of <ulink url="http://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-graph-examples">samples</ulink>
				and unit test cases (if you accessed the sources via 
				<ulink url="http://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-graph">github</ulink> or Maven).
			</para>
			<para>For more information on the samples, see <xref linkend="samples"/>.</para>
		</section>
	</section>
    
    <section id="get-started:help">
		<title>Need Help?</title>
		
		<para>If you encounter issues or you are just looking for an advice, feel free to use one of the links below:</para>
		
		<section id="get-started:help:community">
			<title>Spring Data homepage</title>
			<para>The Spring Data <ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-data">homepage</ulink> provides all the necessary links for information, community forums and code repositories.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="get-started:help:professional">
  		    <title>Professional Support</title>
			<para>Professional, from-the-source support, with guaranteed response time, is available from <ulink url="http://www.springsource.com">SpringSource</ulink>,
			the company behind Spring Data and Spring.  
			</para>
		</section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="get-started:up-to-date">
		<title>Follow the Development</title>
		
		<para>For information on the Spring Data source code repository, nightly builds and snapshot artifacts please see the Spring Data home 
		<ulink url="http://www.springsource.org/spring-data">page</ulink>.   
		</para>
		<para>You can help make Spring Data best serve the needs of the Spring community by interacting with developers through the
		<ulink url="http://forum.springsource.org/forumdisplay.php?f=27">community forums</ulink>.</para>
		<para>If you encounter a bug or want to suggest an improvement, 
		please create a ticket on the <ulink url="https://jira.springframework.org/browse/Spring Data Graph">Spring Data Graph issue tracker</ulink>.</para>
		<para>To stay up to date with the latest news and announcements in the Spring eco system, subscribe to the 
		<ulink url="http://www.springframework.org/">Spring Community Portal</ulink>.</para>
		<para>Lastly, you can follow the <ulink url="http://blog.springsource.com/category/data-access/">SpringSource Data blog</ulink> or the project team on Twitter
		(@<ulink url="http://twitter.com/SpringData">SpringData</ulink>)</para>
	</section>
    
</chapter>
