<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<preface id="about-book">
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="springdatagraph.png" contentwidth="15cm" scalefit="1"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </para>
    <section>
    <title>Foreword: Rod Johnson, CEO of SpringSource</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>Foreword: Emil Eifrem, CEO of Neo Technology</title>
        <para></para>
    </section>
    <section>
    <title>About this Guide Book</title>
    <para>
        Welcome to the Spring Data Graph Guide Book. Thank you for taking the time to get an in depth look into <ulink url="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-graph">Spring Data Graph Library</ulink>. Spring Data Graph is part of the <ulink url="http://springsource.org/spring-data">Spring Data project</ulink> which
        brings the convenient programming model of the Spring Framework to modern (mainly NOSQL) datastores.
 		Spring Data Graph currently provides integration for the <ulink url="http://neo4j.org">Neo4j Graph Database</ulink>.
    </para><para>
        It was written by developers for developers. So hopefully we've created a documentation that is well received by
        our peers.
    </para><para>
        If you have any feedback to the Spring Data Graph Library or this book, please provide it via <ulink url="https://jira.springsource.org/browse/DATAGRAPH">SpringSource JIRA</ulink>,
        the <ulink url="http://forum.springsource.org/forumdisplay.php?f=80">SpringSource NOSQL Forum</ulink>, <ulink
        url="https://github.com/SpringSource/spring-data-graph/issues">github comments or issues</ulink> or the <ulink url="http://neo4j.org/community/list/">Neo4j mailing list</ulink>.
    </para><para>
        This book is presented as a <ulink url="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/DuplexBook.html">duplex book</ulink>, a term coined by <ulink url="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/DuplexBook.html">Martin Fowler</ulink>. A duplex book consists of at least two
        parts. The first part is an easily accessible narrative, that gives the reader an overview of the topics contained
        in the book. It contains lots of examples and more general discussion topics. This should be the only part of
        the book that is required to be read cover-to-cover.
    </para><para>
    We chose a tutorial describing the creation of a web applicaton (cineasts.net) that allows movie enthusiasts to
    find the favorites, rate them, connect with each other and enjoy social features. The application is running on
    Neo4j using Spring Data Graph and the well known Spring Web Stack.
</para><para>
        The second part is the classic reference documentation containing the detailed information about the library.
        It discusses the programming model, the underlying assumptions, used toolset (like aspectj) as well as the APIs
        for the object-graph mapping and the template approach. The reference docs should be mainly used to look up
        concrete bits of information or to dig deeper into certain topics.
    </para>
    </section>
</preface>
