<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="reference_programming-model:indexing">
    <title>Indexing</title>

    <para>
        The Neo4j graph database can use different index providers for exact lookups and fulltext searches. Lucene is
        used as default index provider implementation. There is support for distinct indexes for nodes and relationships
        which can be configured to be of fulltext or exact types.
    </para>

    <section>
        <title>Exact and Numeric Index</title>
    <para>
        Using the standard Neo4j API, Nodes and Relationships and their indexed field-value combinations
        have to be added manually to the appropriate index. When using Spring Data Graph, this task is simplified by
        eased by applying an <code>@Indexed</code> annotation on entity fields. This will result in updates to the
        index on every change.
    </para><para>
        Numerical fields are indexed numerically so that they are available for range queries.
        All other fields are indexed with their string representation.
    </para><para>
        The @Indexed annotation can also set the
        index-name to be used the default index name is the simple class name of the entity. So the same field names
        from different classes don't end up in the same index by default. That would return different domain objects
        for a single index query.
    </para>
    <para>
        Query access to the index happens with the Node- and RelationshipFinders that are created via an instance of
        <code>org.springframework.data.graph.neo4j.repository.DirectGraphRepositoryFactory</code>. The methods
        <code>findByPropertyValue</code> and <code>findAllByPropertyValue</code> work on the exact indexes and
        return the first or all matches. To do range queries, use <code>findAllByRange</code> (please note that
        currently both values are inclusive).
    </para>
    <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
@NodeEntity
class Person {
    @Indexed(indexName = "people")
    String name;

    // automatically indexed numerically
    @Indexed
    int age;

}

NodeFinder<Person> graphRepository = graphRepositoryFactory.createNodeEntityFinder(Person.class);

// exact graphRepository
Person mark = graphRepository.findByProperyValue("people","name","mark");

// numeric range queries
for (Person middleAgedDeveloper : graphRepository.findAllByRange(null, "age", 20, 40)) {
    Developer developer=middleAgedDeveloper.projectTo(Developer.class);
}
]]></programlisting>
        </section>
    <section>
        <title>Fulltext Indexes</title>
        <para>
            Spring Data Graph also supports full-text indexes. By default indexed fields are stored in an exact-lookup
            index. To have them analyzed and prepared for fulltext search, the <code>@Indexed</code> annotation has
            the boolean <code>fulltext</code> attribute. Please note that fulltext-indexes require a separate index name
            as the fulltext-configuration is stored in the index itself.
        </para>
        <para>
            Access to the fulltext index is provided by the <code>findAllByQuery</code> method of the finders. Wildcard
            like * are allowed. Otherwise the fulltext querying rules of the underlying index provider apply. (In most
            cases this will be lucene.
        </para>
        <para>
<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
@NodeEntity
class Person {
    @Indexed(indexName = "person-name", fulltext=true)
    String name;
}

NodeFinder<Person> graphRepository = graphRepositoryFactory.createNodeEntityFinder(Person.class);

// exact graphRepository
Person mark = graphRepository.findAllByQuery("people-search","name","ma*");
]]></programlisting>
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
                Please note that indexes are currently created on demand, so whenever an index that doesn't exist
                is requested from a query or get operation it is created. This is subject to change but has currently
                the implication that those indexes won't be configured as fulltext which causes subsequent fulltext-
                updates to those indexes to fail.
            </para>
        </note>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Raw Index Access</title>
        <para>The raw index for a domain class is also available from <code>GraphDatabaseContext</code> via the
        <code>getIndex</code> method. The second parameter is optional and takes the index-name if it doesn't default
            to the simple domain class name. It returns the Index implementation that is provided by Neo4j.
            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
@Autowired GraphDatabaseContext gdc;

// exact index
Index<Node> personIndex=gdc.getIndex(Person.class,null);
personIndex.add(node,"name","Mark");

Index<Node> namedPersonIndex=gdc.getIndex(Person.class,"people");
namedPersonIndex.get("name","Mark");

// complex range & sort query
namedPersonIndex.query( new QueryContext( NumericRangeQuery.newÍntRange( "age", 20, 40, true, true ) )
                        .sort( new Sort( new SortField( "age", SortField.INT, false ) ) ) );

// fulltext index
Index<Node> personFulltextIndex=gdc.getIndex(Person.class,"person-name",true);
namedPersonIndex.query("name","Ma*");
namedPersonIndex.query("{name:Ma*}");

            ]]></programlisting>

        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Indexing in Neo4jTemplate</title>
        <para>
            Neo4jTemplate also offers index support, providing auto-indexing for fields at creation time of nodes and
            relationships. There is an <code>autoIndex</code> method that can also add indexes for a set of fields in one
            go.
        </para>
        <para>
            For querying the index, the template offers query-methods that take either the exact match parameters or a query
            object / query expression and push the results wrapped uniformly as Paths to the supplied
            <code>PathMapper</code> to be converted or collected.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
